[Music]
hi i'm donna wolfe from nastasia.com
today i'll show you how to do punch
needle for beginners this is a vintage
fiber art technique that allows you to
create an embroidered or rug hook loop
texture on cloth if this is your first
time a punch needle kit works great
because they give you everything you
will need such as a cloth with a printed
design on it plenty of yarn and a punch
needle tool or you can get each of the
supplies on your own the cloth is
usually a stiffer open weave fabric like
monk's cloth for yarn or weaver's cloth
for thinner floss and thread
some cloth has a design printed on it
for you but if not you can trace one
onto the fabric with a disappearing ink
marker or even just pencil sometimes the
cloth has wrinkles or creases in it
carefully run the iron over the creases
to smooth them out try not to use steam
or water so the design doesn't get
smudged
next you'll need a punch needle
a punch needle comes in many different
sizes and styles generally speaking
there is a body section that you hold
onto and the needle part is usually made
of metal on the top
some are adjustable which ultimately
regulates the size of each loop you make
in your finished work this is a
stationary punch needle and this one is
good for worsted or medium weight yarn
and this one is really thin and also
very sharp then there's the needle
threader
unlike traditional embroidery we're
going to work directly from the skein of
either yarn or floss and we don't need
to cut the yarn whatsoever every punch
needle is threaded differently mine
requires the use of a wire
which i will insert into the metal part
of the tool first and then down towards
the bottom of the tool which has a hole
on the bottom
then we take our yarn end and put it
through the wire loop
and then we pull on the wire coming out
of the metal end to fish that yarn up
through the tool and out of the metal
section i've pulled way too much yarn
out so i'm going to pull the yarn from
the skein in to pull some of it back
next i need to fish the yarn through the
little hole in the tool
the direction is very important
we insert the loop through the curved
side first insert the yarn then pull it
out through the hole in the tool
adjust the amount of yarn as needed by
pulling on the bottom section of yarn
i like to hold my tool like a pencil and
drape the yarn across the top of my hand
the yarn from the skein needs to be very
loose and have lots of slack
the hoop is more of a grip type of
embroidery hope
as you might notice there are ridges to
really keep that cloth in place since
we're putting a lot of pressure on the
fabric when we punch the needle through
it
so place your cloth on the circle
without the tightening screw
then place the top loop on and tighten
the screw a bit
then go around the edges and ever so
slightly tug on the cloth to ensure you
have a good solid fit you don't want any
slack in the center of the cloth once
you are ready it's time to take your
threaded tool and begin punching or
pushing the cloth with it it's important
to note that the scooped out side of the
tool will always go in the direction you
are moving push the tool into the cloth
until it can go no further
notice i have a black ridge that stops
my tool carefully pull the tool back out
but don't lift the tip of the tool too
far above the cloth level glide the tip
of that tool along the cloth very gently
then decide on how far apart you want
your next stitch
there's really no right or wrong just
some lengths look better than others on
some designs
push the tool in the cloth again until
the black ridge section your tool might
have a different color
gently pull the tool out but the tip
should still be the height of the cloth
glide it gently over the cloth which by
the way is just a technique to help keep
you from pulling out the loop you just
made i'm going in super slow motion for
this tutorial but once you become
familiar with this you can zip around
the design really quickly
and just keep going in whatever
direction looks best
i'm going to stop right here for a
moment
if you need to take a little break you
can pull your needle out and be sure to
grip the yarn so it doesn't pull from
the other side
on the front side we had straight
stitches and if you notice on the back
we have the little loops let's just say
i don't like what i've done because the
stitches are inconsistent
i can easily pull out one stitch or all
of the stitches like this and then
either start all over again or just pull
back the excess yarn and bring your tool
back to the cloth level again as i start
over i want to show something some
people in instructions might tell you to
start your end in the back instead of
the front like i did the first time
this is completely up to you and i've
been known to have my ends in the front
and some designs and some designs in the
back
and you can just push the tool into the
fabric right over the holes or even in
the same holes from the previous
go-around i'm going to outline this
heart in blue so once i get to the end
of the design it's time to cut the yarn
and change colors unlike knitting and
crocheting where we always have to weave
in our ends with punch needle we just
cut the yarn close to the last stitch
the cloth itself holds the stitches in
place and since these are mostly
decorative items we don't have to worry
about ends coming out in the washer or
dryer that's it for the blue color
now i'm going to fill the heart in with
pink yarn
this time however i want to add some
texture to my work so i'm going to work
from the other side of the cloth
this side will have the straight
stitches while the other side will have
the little loop stitches
in punch needle designs you can keep
everything consistent either with the
straight stitches in the front or the
loops in the front or you can mix and
match loops with straight stitches this
is what is happening on the other side
of the fabric while you are working
those straight stitches
you can see how the little loops are
formed by the tool interacting with the
cloth you'll continue with this process
for all of the yarn colors to make the
design
you can trim the cloth and display the
work in the embroidery hoop or take it
out and sew the cloth to make display
rugs or pillows and more and that's the
basics of punch needle embroidery and
rug making thanks so much for watching
my video please subscribe to my youtube
channel to get notified of new videos
from me each week and if you liked the
video you just watched be sure to check
out my next video which i think you'll
like very much